Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Albums (Album File) circa 1880-circa 1980 (bulk 1860-1920) PR 2
New-York Historical Society
- Sites and scenes, Washington Heights vicinity / collected by Reginold Pelham Bolton, [1910-1930]; 13936 (Volume 261)
  Spine title: Washington Heights, New York City; views in Inwood, Fort Tryon, Fort Washington, Washington Heights, Kingsbridge; Laurel Hill, Fort Clinton and Fort George; "Indian cave" in Inwood Hill Park; view of men working excavating Revolutionary War sites; Dyckman valley; Inwood Valley from Fort George; historic homes and sites including Jumel Mansion, Ambrose Kingsley Home (one view with cow grazing on lawn), "Melbourne," Haven estate, J.J. Audubon home, Billings residence, a castellated home that was in Villas on the Hudson (1860), Nagel homestead, including view of house after a fire, E.A. Poe cottage, Shepard Karpp House in the snow; remains of batteries; views along Broadway including intersection with St. Nicholas, American Geographical Society, American Indian Museum, apartments, Church of the Intercession; Bolton garden at 158th, including views of fences and pergola; Holyrood church at 181st; Seaman Ave., Indian village site; excavating Indian ceremonial site; "Indian caretaker and her grandchildren, Inwood Hill park"; Negro burying ground and Indian dog pits, and a view of human remain in the burying ground, 212th St. and 10th Ave.; snowy lane at 187th and Broadway; Polo Grounds; views from the water tower; small wood-frame homes on Croton St.; views along Spuyten Duyvil, and the Hudson, including views of Riverside Drive including construction, and streets from 135th to 162nd; Harlem River from 201st.; tugs "removing" Broadway swing bridge to 207th Street; Spuyten Duyvil, showing Marble Hill and the Johnson foundry; Marble Hill and U.S. ship canal; New York Central Railroad station and railroad cut; children in yard between Seaman & Prescott (Payson) Ave., a military camp site; reconstructed military hut, Dyckman House Park dedication of playground at Colonial Park, Bussing farm; photographs of drawings and prints of early homes; trees, including tulip trees, historic trees; view of springs; photographers include Gottscho, Geo. Dodd, Chas. Boyer, W. L. Calver, Geo. C. Wheeler, E. Wenzel.
- Pictures of Old New York, [1895]; 13934 (Volume 262)
  Prints, clippings from magazines and other publications, and stationery with view letterhead, including engravings, lithographs, halftones, etching, wood engraving and drypoint, depicting historic sites in Manhattan, including farmsteads, churches, hotels, the stock exchange and other commercial buildings, the Hudson and East Rivers, Central Park, views from and in Brooklyn Heights, cultural buildings including Astor Library, the Crystal Palace, interior of 7th Regt. Armory Fulton Ferry, state prison, The Tombs including interior showing police court, charitable institutions; panorama of the city from Brooklyn; a view of Brady's Gallery of Daguerreotype; Indian village of Manhattans; riot of Astor Place, burning of City Hall; images made between ca. 1820 and ca. 1892.
- [Album of photographs of New York city and vicinity], [1955]-1980; 13932 (Volume 263)
  Articles regarding historic sites, exhibits of photographs, etc., laid in; harbor and waterfront views, including sunsets, ferry terminal, skyline, Statue of Liberty, Ellis Island; aerial views of Manhattan; street scenes including store fronts, a bag lady asleep on a sidewalk, a man passed out on the Bowery, man selling beads on a stoop, the Village art show, San Genaro festival; buildings under construction showing contrast of 19th century buildings with International style office towers; historic buildings including Customs House and others; churches, parks; ocean liners at dock, Hudson River; night views of lights and neon signs, including Times Square and Christmas decorations; Polish parade; Penn station, including interior (1965) and construction of Madison Square Garden; Stern's department store, including woman and girl shopping; view looking north at West Point; Central Park, including skating rink, Belvedere, fountain and zoo; looking north from West Point; cats; Ebbets Field and the Polo Grounds; Fort Tryon Park; Rye Beach Amusements.
- [Bradley Martin Ball], 1897; 13930 (Volume 264)
  Copies of portraits of Mrs. Bradley Martin (Cornelia Sherman Martin), the hostess, and her guests at a costume ball held in 1897; some portraits with Falk credit; most guests dressed as European royalty, also includes one man dressed as a samurai or Japanese aristocrat.
- Snap shots -- Book V, from Summer 1936 to [1940], 1936-1940; 13928 (Volume 265)
  Snapshots of the Barber family, including views at their home on Park Avenue, in Ridgewood; family and friends at vacation house at New London, Mel knitting, family with dogs, the pier and waterfront, a water bicycle, beach views, Ethel Barber's birthday party; views in Oslo; Billie at Jones Beach; a trip to California, including views in San Francisco, fishing in San Francisco bay, Mt. Tamalpais, Los Gatos and Montezuma School; portraits of family dogs; Lal in school play; leaving on Queen Mary for England; Stranahan Estate, Westport Connecticut, including house and grounds, pool, beach, Sound, boathouse, formal garden, pond, barbecue, interior views, gardener and other household employees; greeting cards, place cards, presents for Ethel's birthday, damage after 1938 hurricane; Billie at work in her studio; get together of the Red Bag Club, 1939; sleet storm at Ridgefield; Ed and the chief of police of Havana. See also album #266-273.
- Ethel Amweg Scott Barber, Book I, [1880-1939]; 13926 (Volume 266)
  Portraits of Blanch Ethel Amweg, who went by Ethel; includes baby and childhood pictures with her mother and siblings, and at seaside entertainments, images of her at 15 and 17, and slightly later, including her in various costumes, including men's clothing; Ethel and friend dressed for masquerade; Ethel in what is probably her debutante dress, and possibly in her wedding dress to Walter Scott; views of the house decorated for her wedding, and her wedding presents; portraits of Ethel with her daughter Willette (Billie); portraits from travels, including Man Ray portraits; oter photographers include Underwood and Underwood, Kaiden and others; portrait of Ethel in her wedding dress for her wedding to Edward Barber; portraits made in Boston, San Francisco, Paris, Holywood, Florida, New York; views of her apartment on Park Ave., see also Album #190; includes early color photographs; portraits of Ethel, Billie and Mel outdoors at home. See also album #265, 267-273
- Willette-Ann Scott Barber, Book I, 1911-1937; 13924 (Volume 267)
  Portraits of Willette Ann Scott Barber, "Billie" born September 12, 1911. Views of her nursery; snapshots and portraits of Billie between ages 2 months and 28 years; snapshots of Billie in costume, in a school portrait, with Christmas tree, on horseback, in Monte Carlo; drawing of her by Christus Simatos; at the opera with Herman Goldman; on board ship with her dog; sketch by John Peter; proofs for John Powers and for Arthur William Brown story; at Atlantic Beach Club with James Blazely Blakley and "Mel"; snapshots at Central Park and at the Beach [Jones Beach]; sitting at desk writing; proofs of photographs by Kaiden Studios, some with Mel. See also album #265, 266, 268-273.
- [Barber Family Album of Hawaii], 1898; 13922 (Volume 268)
  Commercially produced photographs by Davey Photo. Co., one hand-colored, depicting buildings and scenery on Hawaii, including public ceremony with reviewing stand decorated with American, British and other flags; streets and buildings in Honolulu; Iolani Palace; Dr. Murray's Residence; Waikiki; scenery portraits of Hula dancers; man in army uniform in front of small house; small, possibly amateur photographs, including a picnic, shore and cliff views, a military camp; ships and outriggers, soldiers, including one on horseback. See also album #265-267, 269-273.
- [Barber Family Album], [1860-1899]; 13920 (Volume 269)
  Portraits of members of the Barber, Townsend, and Morton families, and including James Fennimore Cooper and Gen. Winfield Scott Hancock, officers in front of a tent, the West Point Class of 1867, two views of an exhibition showing cannons and flags; series of group portraits where the women and men are dressed in the costume of various nationalities including Chinese, Scottish, Spanish, Russian, Turkish, French, Bedouin, and Native Americans and women dressed in costumes representing soldiers, maids, and a patriotic tableau. See also album #265-268, 270-273.
- Photographs of Mr. & Mrs. Edw. J. Barber's apartments, 1120 Park Ave., New York, after 1925; 13918 (Volume 270)
  Interior views of the apartment showing foyer, living room, dining room (with murals showing Italian scenes), library, game room, and the bedrooms of Billie (Willette A. Scott), Ethel and Edward, with Ethel seated at her desk in one view; accompanying copies of articles describing the marriage of Ethel Scott and Edward Barber in 1925; Art Deco design on blue cover. See also album #265-269, 271-273.
- [Townsend and Barber family album], [1866-1889]; 13916 (Volume 271)
  Cartes-de-visite, cabinet cards and tintypes of the Barber, Townsend, Tremain, Berry, Thayer, Johnson, Van Rensselaer, Crosby, Martin, Pierson, Black, Johnson, Wilder, Van Vechten families, and others including James Fennimore Cooper and his sister as children. See also album #265-270, 272, 273.
- West Point, Book of the class of 1867, 13914 (Volume 272)
  Faculty and cadets at West Point, 1867, each identified, and including group portraits of the class, and views of West Point scenery.
- [Thayer family album], [1880-1889]; 13912 (Volume 273)
  Cabinet card photographs of the Thayer, Townsend, Rensselaer, Ewing, Andrew, Morton, and Church families, and others; album bound in purple velvet. See also album #51, 136, 137, 265-272.
- [E.B. Child album], [1890-1909]; 13910 (Volume 274)
  Includes images printed in both gelatin silver and cyanotype, and includes early Kodak views; farm views including winter scenes, men digging a trench, corn field, boy and goat, man with apples, fields, man in false beard with wheelbarrow; street views include a parade, homes, including backyard scenes, man with ponies, carriages; beach scenes and Clason Point Baths, gospel streetcar, and tent meeting, churches; interior views including a Christmas tree; portraits include women with tennis rackes, man with cat, men and women in graduation costume, men in costume or false beards, etc. emoting for the camera; many of the photographs are faded; small. See also album #79-81,101, 149, 154.
- [Schieffelin family and friends, Bar Harbor, Me., and Scarborough N.Y.], 1896; 13908 (Volume 275)
  Photographs by Jay Schieffelin; cyanotypes and gelatin silver prints; children with ponies and tricycle; Miss McLane's class of children; group portrait of the Committee for "In the Hollow of his Hand" Mission; Lea McI. Luguer and Anne Low Pierrepont posing together on their engagement; Willie and Margaret Schieffelin with mother and sister Mary in baby carriage and other portraits; Moncure Robinson; woman with terrier; Schieffelin family at Woodlea in Scarborough, including woman on bicycle and children with goat cart; Edith and Ernesto on their engagement; Woodlea decorated for Edith's wedding; views of Beechwood, home of H. Walter Webb, Scarborough.
- [Newtown High School] Mandel Bros. Contracting Corporation, 1956; 13906 (Volume 276.1)
  Photographs by Mal Gurian Associates, photographers, of the progress of the construction of Newtown High School in 1956.
- [Newtown High School] Mandel Bros. Contracting Corporation, 1956; 13905 (Volume 276.2)
  Documentation of subcontractor submissions for approval, drawings submissions, etc. for Newtown High School construction.
- The University Club Souvenir, 1904, 13903 (Volume 277)
  Twelve photographs depicting the University Club, including one exterior view showing carriages in front, and 11 interior views showing various richly appointed rooms, including a pool, billiard room, library, dining room, meeting and sitting rooms.
- [Collins scrapbook of snapshots and postcards], [1906-1908]; 13901 (Volume 278)
  Includes snapshots on board a ship, including women visiting, men in uniform and in costume for Halloween, a polo match, men in aprons waiting on women, men on barren outdoor scene, possibly in Panama, view of the Andes, men hunting; postcards of Central and South America, Canada, the United States, and the largest group from Japan, some with messages visible; also includes two Howard Chandler Christy postcards.
- Photographs [album of San Francisco views and people, Hawaiian scenes and celebrities, including royalty and Japanese envoys], 1861; 13899 (Volume 279)
- Deo duce rerro comitante, Clinton S. Sears, U.S.A [West Point, Class of 1867, and 1868], 1867-1868; 13897 (Volume 280)
  Photographs of faculty, students and buildings; annotations with each image giving student's commission, retirement date and rank, marriages, and death date.
- Our Wedding, Karen and Bob, June 3, 1972. Isacson, Henry, photographer., 13895 (Volume 281)
  Wedding album, bound in white with gold lettering on cover; color photographs approx. 7.5 x 9.5 in. or less; bride in front of mirror, with bridesmaids, a view showing bridal gown with train, bride with parents, with dog, arriving at church, marriage ceremony and communion, group portrait of wedding party, bride and groom, reception photographs, cutting the cake, dancing, etc.
- [Vanderbilt costume ball], undated; 13893 (Volume 282)
- The streets of old New York: Twenty-four scenes and stories originally appearing in the Antiques section of the New York Sun., [1950]; 13891 (Volume 283)
  Issued in portfolio; title from cover; reproductions of drawings by J. Ernest Brierly of scenes, historic homes, taverns, roads, many representing the period of New Amsterdam
- Album collection of photographic portraits of Trans-Atlantic Celebrities, Made in Europe during the Summer of 1869, by William J. Florence, and presented to A. Oakey Hall, Mayor of New York, by Joseph H. Tooker, 13889 (Volume 284)
- Photographic Senatorial Album of the State of New York, 1872-73. Published by R. E. Churchill, photographer, Albany, N.Y., 1872-1873; 13887 (Volume 285)
- Progress Photos, South Ferry, 1955-1958; 13885 (Volume 286.1)
- Progress Photos, South Ferry, 1955-1958; 13884 (Volume 286.2)
  Construction photographs of the South Ferry building (Contract 2881A); men from various trades at work; general views of the project; details of demolition and construction and of various rooms and areas of the buildings; 8x10 images in 3-ring binders.
- Photographs, ES to Libby B. Knox [Portraits, Civil War officers], undated; 13882 (Volume 287)
  Cartes-de-visite.
- [Wainwright album], [1860-1879]; 13880 (Volume 288)
  Cartes-de-visite, mostly unidentified, including some prominent persons, including Grant and other Civil War Generals, and others; a caricature, European scenes and art, sentimental views.
- Anglo-Catholic Episcopate in America, [1840-1870]; 13878 (Volume 289)
  Engravings and albumen prints of clergy, primarily bishops, by various engravers and photographers, including R.W. Doson, T. Gimbrede, W. Main, J.F.E. Prud'homme, J. Gurney & Son, Rockwood & Co. and others.
- [Alice W. Bartlett album], [1870-1939]; 13876 (Volume 290)
  Photographs of Alice Bartlett and members of the Stinson, Smith and Harvey families, including wedding and graduation pictures; mostly amateur photography.
- Yo-semite Valley California / by Gustavus Fagersteen, 1887; 13874 (Volume 291)
  Views in Yosemite including waterfalls, rocks, mountains, people riding coach through an arch cut in a big tree; composite photograph of people in "Big Tree room, including couple playing guitar, others seated at tables or in front of fireplace, lined with views of Yosemite; issued in green portfolio.
- Souvenier [sic] of 1876. Greatorex, Eliza Pratt, 1819-1897, artist., 13872 (Volume 292)
  Lithographs, including cover, with various scenes from Independence Hall, Old Witch House, Salem, David Burnes house in Washington, D.C., Old Swede's Church, Philadelphia, Mount Vernon, Christ Church in Alexandria, Arlington Heights; probably issued in portfolio, now bound.
- Engravings of the '40s, views of the British Isles, [1840-1849]; 13870 (Volume 293)
  Etchings and engravings of scenes in Great Britain, primarily in Scotland, including Yorkshire, Westmoreland, Curbria, Liverpool, Cambridge, London, Wales, Ireland and other locations; a menagerie, castles, abbeys, bridges, monuments, landscapes, including lochs, waterfalls, cliffs; publishers and engravers include J. Menzies, T & W. McDowall, J. Shearer, R.S. Michie, J.L. Smith, J. & F. Harwood, Rock & Co, J. Gellatty, James Mitchell and Co., W. Forrest, J. Mason, W.H. Lizars, David Nimmo, T. Stewart, J. Johnstone, A. Dole, Henry Cave, E. Finden, B. Carter, S. Rawle, W. Cooke, J. Newman, Russsell and Cowan, and others; also includes handcolored views of New Haven fishermen and other scenes.
- [Album of clippings depicting ships], [1930-1939]; 13868 (Volume 294)
  River Steamers, including images of the Clermont, sailing ships, ocean liners, sailing and steam yachts, ferries, primarily centered in New York and the Northeast; includes earlier illustrations, as well as contemporary photographs.
- Constitution. Burton, James, photographer., 1901; 13866 (Volume 295)
  Views of the Yacht "Constitution" during the 1901 season, including at Newport May 30 and June 4, the Commodores, Cup July 22 at Glen Cove, Astor Cup at Newport, July 29; each image with blind stamp of the photographer James Burton; has Harold Godwin bookplate and card with flags and "Constitution" printed on it affixed to inside front cover of Album.
- [Album of clippings of cartoons from the New Yorker (?)], [1930-1939]; 13864 (Volume 296)
  Cartoons by William Steig, Otto Soglow, Peter Arno, Gluyas Williams Abner Dean and others.
- [Album of portraits of John Jay], undated; 13862 (Volume 297)
  Copy photographs of paintings, prints, an event handkerchief, and a bust depicting John Jay, many with sources and cropping marks, articles and letters regarding likenesses of him, a copy of No. 28, Publications of the Order of Colonial Lords of Manors in American: The Jay Family, by Laura Jay Wells, 1938, and a program from the Sesquicentennial Celebration of the Supreme Court of the United States; all housed in loose-leaf binder; laid in are a family tree of the Jay Family and "Jack's Panorama of Firth Avenue from 57th to 91st drawn in 1903" showing houses on Fifth Avenue, drawn on lined paper.
- [Scrapbook of clippings and souvenirs], [1890-1911]; 13860 (Volume 298)
  Portraits of politicians, bureaucrats, businessmen, and baseball players; views of buildings and fences covered with posters and bills, and a building housing a bill posters' business, bill poster's advertisement, Buffalo Bill invitation, bill posters' association dinner, and other advertising related persons; views of Tarpon Springs, and Palm Springs Florida; views of Long Beach and other Long Island locales; series of portraits of little girls sitting at Smith typewriters, including ethnic stereotypes of African American and Chinese girls.
- 1881 Photographic annual of the state officers, Senate & Assembly of the state of New York. By the Notman Photographic Co., Albany, N.Y., 13858 (Volume 299)
  Photo-montages of the Senate and Assembly of New York, with key to photographs.
- Scrapbooks of clippings, lithographs and photographs of New York locations and people, [1840] and later; 13856 (Volume 300.1)
- Scrapbooks of clippings, lithographs and photographs of New York locations and people, [1840] and later; 13855 (Volume 300.2)
  Clippings from magazines and newspapers, including German-language press, certificates, business cards, letterhead, maps, advertisements; items depict places, including taverns, homes, theatres, markets, tenements, churches, government and commercial buildings; events such as the ship's quarantine in 1851, Purim celebration, battle between rival gangs, parades, solar eclipse, fires and other disasters; some portraits. Many maps.
- Wedding Book, volume 2, 1913-1915; 13853 (Volume 301)
  Scrapbook compiled by Evelyn Witherbee documenting the weddings of friends; includes invitations, thank you notes, newspaper clippings and snapshots of Gwynne-Van Schaick, Baylis-Aurebach, Lawrence-Atwell, Von Friesen-Scheitlin, Linn-Blair, Pyne-Landon, Field-Marshall, Sloane-Lee marriages.
- Photographic views of Hudson Square, 1866-1867; 13851 (Volume 302)
  "Six photographic views of Hudson Square, St. John's Park, presented by the Vestry of Trinity Church July 19, 1867, in Port-folio"; Beach St. and park, west from Varick; Hudson St. and park; looking west across the center of St. John's Park; looking east from center of St. John's Park; St. John's Park, Laight St. side from Hudson; Varick Street and park from Laight St.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1916-1918; 13849 (Volume 303.1)
  Is embossed "Photographs Vol. II," Angela as a baby, at Aratoma Farm, Katonah, views at a cottage in Summerville, S.C. plantation homes, cabins, a fort, unidentified African Americans, homes in Beaufort, S.C., snapshots at a wedding, views at Happy Valley Farm, including the gardens, family, building stone pump house, travels in Plattsburg, N.Y. and Stockbridge, Mass., Robert Fowler in uniform, R.O.T.C. training in Plattsburg, picnics and beach views, biplanes at a field in Garden City, L.I.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1919-1925; 13848 (Volume 303.2)
  Fowler family snaphots, including children, babies, Godwin and other families; farm and garden scenes; Katonah Welcome Home parade, including World War I soldiers and nurses, floats, a band concert, May 31, 1919; views in Massachusetts including historic homes and buildings, and interiors; snow scenes; views in Connecticut and Rhode Island; horses; construction scenes; Rippowam School field day and play, 1923.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1921-1922; 13847 (Volume 303.3)
  Fowler family snapshots, including children; trip to the Mediterranean, Spain, France, Italy, Monaco, England, including churches and cloisters, castles, chateaus, villas, cottages, gardens and street scenes; views in Rheims showing World War I destruction.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1916-1920s], 1925-1929; 13846 (Volume 303.4)
  Hiking and hunting in Maine, blizzard of 1926 in Katonah, dogs and children, skating, sledding, etc.; other views at the Fowler home in Katonah, including tree house and bird feeder, Banksia roses, horseback riding; African American domestics Annie, Dorothy, and Ann Eliza; Waring family members and views in Charleston, and other S.C. locations; Rippowam School activities, including plays and field days; swimming, boating and beach views; Godwin family members, Godurie family members; vacation views in Florida, Massachusetts, Long Island, Rhode Island, Cuba; views of New Orleans; Whitman family members; Warren family members; gardens, including family working in garden and stacking firewood. See also album #89, 304-307.
- [Robert Ludlow Fowler family albums, 1932-1936], 1932-1933; 13844 (Volume 304.1)